A Guide to the Reports of the Virginia Dept. of Juvenile Justice, 1988-1998
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Reports of the Virginia Dept. of Juvenile Justice, 1988-1998
The Library of Virginia
53584
1.35 cu. ft. (3 boxes)
Library of Virginia Board
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession 53584 transferred by Charles Kehoe, former Director of the Virginia Dept. of Juvenile Justice, March 25, 2022.
Historical Information
The Dept. of Juvenile Justice was created as the Dept. of Youth and Family Services on 1 July 1990 (Code of Virginia 66-1). Previously, the department operated as the Division of Youth and Family Services within the Department of Corrections. The named changed to the Dept. of Juvenile Justice in 1996. The Dept. of Juvenile Justice is headed by a Director who answers to the Governor. The department also operates under the heading of the Secretary of Public Safety.
The mission of the Dept. of Juvenile Justice is to "protect the public through a balanced approach of accountability and comprehensive services that prevent and reduce delinquency through partnerships with families, schools, communities, law enforcement, and others, while providing opportunities for delinquent youth to become responsible and productive citizens." The Dept. of Juvenile Justice operates the commonwealth's juvenile detention facilities, oversees delinquency, gang, and substance abuse programs, as well as group and transitional homes. Initiatives supported by the Dept. of Juvenile Justice include detention assessment and the Youth Assessment and Screening Instrument, the Detention Re-entry Project, the Juvenile Detention Alternatives Initiative, and the Ombudsman Program to assist families of incarcerated youth.
The State Board of Youth Services was also created in 1989 (Code of Virginia, 66-4) and consists of seven members appointed by the Governor. The Board meets five times each year at locations around the state. The name changed to the Board of Youth and Family Services in 1990, and the Board was renamed the Board of Juvenile Justice in 1996. Title 66 of the Code went into effect on 1 July 1990, though the Board was formed and began meeting in July 1989.
The Board of Juvenile Justice was created to ensure the development and implementation of a long-range youth services policy. The Board advises the Governor, the Director of the Department of Juvenile Justice, and the General Assembly on matters related to youth services. The Board of Juvenile Justice is a policy board, and is charged by law with adopting and monitoring regulations and policies for juvenile justice programs. The Board works closely with the Department of Juvenile Justice to develop new policies and review existing policies ones.
As part of a reorganization of the executive branch of state govenment, the Dept. of Correctional Education was eliminated by the General Assembly (SB 678) effective July 2012. The bill divided the provision and administration of education in correctional institutions between the Dept. of Corrections and the Dept. of Juvenile Justice, with suprevision by a newly created Division of Correctional Education within the Dept. of Juvenile Justice.
Scope and Content
Reports, 1988-1998, are housed in 3 boxes, and were maintained by the Director of the Virginia Dept. of Juvenile Justice. This collection includes fifteen reports related to juvenile detention. The majority of the reports were created while the agency was the Virginia Dept. of Youth and Family Services. Also included are two 11 x 17 posters, 1994: "Youth Begins with You", a promotional poster; and a framed sketch of of tiger that was displayed in the the General Assembly Building for an art show entitled "Expressions Arts and Crafts by Virginia Learning Center Youth".
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Reports, 1988-1998.
  - Report: Northern Virginia Secure Detention Needs Assessment (Virginia Dept. of Corrections), 1988 Nov 1. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Report: Managing the Development of Community Corrections (U.S. Dept. of Justice/Crime and Justice Foundation), 1990 Feb 1. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Report: Cost Management Process for Placement of Youth in Public and Private Residential and Non-Residential Programs - Legislative Study Budget Item No. 716 (Virginia Dept. of Youth and Family Services), 1990 Oct 15. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Report: Cost Management Process for Operational Support of City, County and Regional Group Homes and Detention Facilities - Legislative Study Budget Item No. 718 (Virginia Dept. of Youth and Family Services), 1990 Oct 15. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Report: Report on Learning Center Escape and AWOL Incidents (Virginia Dept. of Youth and Family Services), 1992 Feb 1. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Report: Minority Representation in Virginia's Learning Centers (Virginia Dept. of Youth and Family Services), 1992 May 1. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Report: Learning Center Standards Adopted by the Board of Juvenile Justice (Virginia Dept. of Youth and Family Services), 1992 July 15. (Box 1)
  - Report: Detention Crisis Initiatives - A Response to Crowding and Access (Virginia Dept. of Youth and Family Services - Detention Task Force), 1992 Aug 6. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Report: Secure Detention Study - A Profile of Admissions by the Court Service Unit in May 1992 (Virginia Dept. of Youth and Family Services), 1992 Sept 1. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Report: Certification Regulations Adopted by the Board of Juvenile Justice (Virginia Dept. of Youth and Family Services), 1992 Sept 9. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Report: Substance Abuse Programs - Annual Report (FY 1991-1992), 1992 Oct 1. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Report: Minority Representation in the Intake Process of the Juvenile Justice System (Virginia Dept. of Youth and Family Services), 1992 Nov 1. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Report: Emergency Minimum Standards for the Detention of Juveniles in Jails and Lockups (Virginia Dept. of Youth and Family Services), 1993 May 21. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Report: A Legislative Study to Assess the Impact of Closing State-Operated Halfway Houses and Contracting for Service (Virginia Board of Youth and Family Services), 1993 Nov 1. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Report: Juvenile Detention Program Design and Planning Study - Cities of Suffolk and Franklin, Counties of Brunswick, Greensville, Isle of Wight and Southampton (MMMDesign and Powell Consulting Services), 1998 Apr 29. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Posters, 1994.
  - Poster: Expressions of Arts and Craft by Virgini Learning Center Youth - Sketch of Tiger, 1994 Jan 31. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Poster: "Youth Begins With You", 1994 July 1. (Box 3, Folder 2)